Guide to the Joanne Grant research files,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Joanne Grant Research Files,
1963-1968.
Grant, Joanne
1.44 linear feet (3 document boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, University Archives New York, NY. 10027
6892009
UA#0141
This collection consists of the working materials Joanne Grant, a journalist and activist, collected for the research and publication of her 1969 book Confrontation on Campus: Columbia Pattern for the New Protest (New York: New American Library, 1969).
Biographical Note
Joanne Grant, born in 1930 in Ithaca, New York to a biracial mother and white father, graduated from Syracuse University with a degree in history and journalism. At 27, Grant traveled throughout the Soviet Union and China, defying state bans on travel to Communist countries, seeking alternatives to an American political system that perpetuated segregation and class divides. Grant was deeply interested in finding organizing and mobilizing tools through which to address the racial and economic inequities of American democracy. Upon her return, the young journalist briefly assisted W.E.B. DuBois, noted black scholar, intellectual, and activist. DuBois, who had left the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), an organization he had founded, as the leadership became more mainstream, sought increasingly more radical alliances for his activism. Undoubtedly, DuBois' mounting frustrations with the unfulfilled promises of equality through integration and his profound interest in creating international Communist alliances, influenced Grant.
With DuBois' referral, Grant took a position as a journalist at the Leftist New York weekly The National Guardian in 1960 and traveled throughout the South to detail Civil Rights struggles for the paper, writing on Freedom Summer, the Citizenship School movement, marches and voter registration drives. Her reporting connected to her to the folks of the Student Non-violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), a militant student organization that used direct action to protest segregation, and to SNCC's founder, Ella Baker. Baker, who had gotten her start as an activist in the NAACP some twenty-five years before, had persuaded Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. to hold a college conference in 1960, on the heels of sporadic youth action to desegregate college campuses. The symposium birthed SNCC, and Baker left the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) to become the young organization's advisor. Impressed by the expansive direct action program SNCC was implementing, Grant joined the organization, both as a journalist and activist. Her journalism for The Guardian provided a platform for SNCC to publicize their work and the repressive responses of politicians, law enforcement and white citizens.
She married Victor Rabinowitz in 1967, a New York lawyer and activist who defended many Leftist organizations throughout the various freedom struggles of the 1960s including leaders of the Weather Underground, SNCC, and high-profile communists. Grant's experiences with SNCC and the Black freedom movement informed her comprehensive document- based history of the black struggle against oppression entitled Black Protest: 350 Years of History, Documents, and Analyses (New York: Fawcett, 1968). Her involvement with SNCC also led her to cover and participate in the student uprisings at Columbia University in 1968. The result was her history and analysis of the strike in Confrontation on Campus: The Columbia Pattern for the New Protest. Evident in her writings is Ms. Grant's overwhelming desire to find new means through which to fight oppression and inequality within the American democratic system.
Grant and Rabinowitz traveled extensively, including a trip to Cuba where Grant charmed Castro into allowing them to accompany the Cuban president on a leg of a speaking tour throughout the country. Her later work, a film entitled Fundi (1981) and later book, Ella Baker: Freedom Bound (New York: Wiley, 1998), were both dedicated to exploring the life and grassroots activism of SNCC founder Ella Baker.
Scope and Content
This collection is a repository of Joanne Grant's research materials for her 1969 book Confrontation on Campus: The Columbia Pattern for the New Protest. The collection contains both Grant's notes taken throughout the Columbia revolt, as well as collected research materials. These materials consist of Strike Coordinating Committee fliers, agendas, leaflets and official statements. In addition, the collection includes the responses of faculty, administration and community members to the strike. The collection also contains materials from the Independent Committee on Vietnam at Columbia University, student protest files against Columbia's involvement in the war. The materials consist of fliers, letters, telegrams and pictures.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series.
Series I: Research Materials on Columbia University Student Uprisings, 1965-1968
Subseries I.1: Pre-uprising 1963-1968
Subseries I.2: Uprising 1966-1968
Series II: Materials collected from Laura Foner, 1968
Series III. Photographs of Columbia University Student Uprisings, 1968
Subjects
Columbia University--Administration.; Columbia University--History.; Columbia University.--Student Strike, 1968.; Columbia University.--Students.; Columbia University.--Alumni and alumnae--Societies,etc.; Columbia University.--Students--Political activity.; Columbia University.--Students' Afro-American Society.; Columbia Spectator.; Columbia University Student Coordinating Committee.; Columbia-Barnard Citizenship Council.; Committee for the Defense of Property Rights.; Community Action Committee.; Black Panther Party.; College students--New York (State)--New York--Political activity.; December Fourth Movement.; Employees for March 25th.; Faculty Peace Action Committee.; Morningside Housing Committee.; Progressive Labor Party.; Radical Faculty Group.; Student Mobilization Committee (U.S.).; Student Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam a.k.a. SMC.; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.).; Students for a Free Campus.; Students for a Reconstructed University a.k.a. SRU.; Grant, Joanne.; Kirk, Grayson L. (Grayson Louis), 1903-; Rudd, Mark.; Civil rights movements.--United States--History--20th century.; Draft resisters--Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975.; Peace movements.; Social movements.; Student-Administrators relationships.; Student Movements--New York (State)--New York.; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975.; Articles.; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Ephemera.; Handbills.; Newsletters.; Press Releases.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located offsite.
This collection has no restrictions. Some personal material may be restricted due to the presence of personal names and information.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Columbia University Student Uprisings, 1963-1968
  This series contains materials that document the issues leading up to the uprising and provides a chronology of student, faculty, community and administrative involvement in the 1968 strike. The folders within each subseries are arranged alphabetically.
  - Subseries I.1. Pre-uprising, 1963-1968
    This subseries provides early documentation of anti-Vietnam War sentiment on Columbia University’s campus including the official documentation of the Independent Committee on Vietnam as well as student responses to Columbia’s class ranking and draft policies. Finally there are five spiral bound notebooks of handwritten notes taken before and during the student strikes.
    - Draft Ranking--Student Responses, circa 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - National Reserve Officers Training Corps, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Notebooks, 1968, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Vietnam--Independent Committee at Columbia University, 1965-1967, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Subseries I.2. Uprising, 1966-1968
    contains a compilation of fliers, SCC memoranda, meeting minutes, and statements, press releases, correspondence, and public statements documenting the student uprisings. A full chronology is followed by the materials of various student groups: the Strike Coordinating Committee, black students and students from Barnard College. Many of the student newsletters are addressed to Morris Grossner, a Columbia University student at the time and a leader in Columbia’s chapter of the Students for a Democratic Society (SDS). These materials are followed by letters of support and various other responses of those involved in the strike, as well as plans for the restructuring of the University. Also included are submissions, addressing racism, black students and the labor movement, by Columbia University students to the magazine China Features in Peking.
    - China Features--Submissions, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Chronology
      - Student Uprisings, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Student Uprisings, 1968 March-June (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Student Uprisings, 1968 March-June (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Involvement
      - Barnard, 1968 April-May (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Black Students, 1968 April (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Responses
      - Administration, 1968 April-May (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Community, 1968 April-May (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Faculty, 1968 March-May (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Parents, 1968 May (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Students, 1968 April-May (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Restructuring of Columbia University, 1968 May (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Strike Coordinating Committee
      - Meeting Minutes, 1968 March - June (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Official Statements and Pamphlets, 1968 March-June (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Strike Education Committee, 1968 May-June (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Surveys--Anthropology Department, 1968 April (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series II: Materials Collected from Laura Foner, 1968
  This series contains research materials collected from Laura Foner, a Columbia University graduate student and member of SNCC. The papers that were contributed by Foner are marked in the top right hand corner of each page with her initials: LF.
  - Administration, 1968 April-May (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Columbia Students for a Democratic Society (SDS)--Working Materials, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Graduate Student Union--Support and Responses, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Strike Coordinating Committee
    - Press Releases, 1968 April- May (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - “The Rational Inquirer”, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Support and Responses, 1968 April-May (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Strike Education Committee--Class Schedules, 1968 April-May (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series III: Photographs, 1968
  Photographs used by Grant in her 1969 book on Columbia University student uprisings Confrontation on Campus. Most of the images are annotated on the back.
  - Photographs--Columbia University Student Uprisings, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)